<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Magento | Max's Thoughts]]></title>
  <link href="http://maxbucknell.github.io//categories/magento/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://maxbucknell.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-07T11:14:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://maxbucknell.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[me@maxbucknell.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Front End Dependency Management in Magento]]></title>
    <link href="http://maxbucknell.github.io/2014/03/06/front-end-dependency-management-in-magento/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T20:54:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://maxbucknell.github.io/2014/03/06/front-end-dependency-management-in-magento</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while now, I&rsquo;ve been wanting to develop a system for managing front end
dependencies for the sites we make at work.</p>

<p>It may seem obvious to use Grunt with some build stage, glomming AMDs together
and spitting out a file at the end. If you want to get really snazzy, then
perhaps you could generate one for the scripts loaded on every page, and then
another one for the scripts loaded on each page.</p>

<p>Yeah, that would be nice. But Magento already has a system for managing front
end assets. The problem is that it&rsquo;s <strong>terrible</strong>. Further, for websites of the
size we make in the time frames we make them in, that just isn&rsquo;t practical.
This is made even more problematic by the fact that Magento is extremely
modular, and including any module on any page will necessitate more JavaScript
being added to the page. Any attempt at a build stage has to take place on the
back end, and it has to be automatic.</p>

<p>Now, I&rsquo;m going to be critical here. Before I begin ripping into our way of life,
I want to make it clear that this is not really anyone&rsquo;s fault. I&rsquo;m certainly
not throwing blame here, and I don&rsquo;t want it to be interpreted that way. Magento
is getting a bit long in the tooth now, and I don&rsquo;t want it to be left behind.
Most of its JavaScript was written in 2007 by PHP developers, and it shows. It&rsquo;s
even using an outdated style of Prototype code.</p>

<h3>What&rsquo;s Wrong With the Status Quo?</h3>

<p>Magento&rsquo;s layout has a system for inserting scripts, but only in the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code>
element. Unless you&rsquo;re doing something nonstandard, every script loaded on the
page will block the display of actual content.</p>

<p>There is a second method, which combines all scripts loaded into one file before
it dispatches. This is a preference in the admin section of Magento, and it
certainly helps. It&rsquo;s nonideal, though, because, we might not want to condense
things into one file. Sure, that reduces HTTP requests, but that is
<a href="http://blog.getify.com/obsessions-http-request-reduction/">not necessarily the goal</a>. The goal is a shorter load speed.</p>

<p>We might not want to condense things into one file because we are loading the
Prototype library on every page, but it&rsquo;s not going to ever be cached on the
frontend, since every page now has different JavaScript. The same problem may
even apply to CSS, since certain modules include their own CSS, in a separate
file.</p>

<p>While we&rsquo;re on the topic of loading JavaScript, why doesn&rsquo;t Magento load its
libraries like Prototype and Scriptaculous from a CDN? Don&rsquo;t trust them? I can
almost guarantee you that your servers will go down before <a href="https://developers.google.com/speed/libraries/devguide#prototype">Google&rsquo;s</a>, and
that if <a href="http://cdnjs.com/libraries/prototype/">Cloudfare</a> are having issues, you&rsquo;ll be more worried about your DNS.</p>

<p>Next in my list of issues is that there is no dependency management beyond the
page level. You want your script to depend on <code>validation.js</code>? Well, include it
and pray. Most of the time, this works out because of the way Magento reads
the layout xml, and the order it goes in usually works. All core dependencies
are satisfied. I&rsquo;m pretty sure this is the reason nothing more substantial has
been developed. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/12613245/2132205">But it&rsquo;s needed</a>.</p>

<p>Magento uses a lot of inlined scripts, and this is annoying. I have a
<code>TypeError</code> in line 589 of <code>index.php</code>? Well, I&rsquo;d better find the id of the
element I&rsquo;m working with and Cmd+f for it. Then pick whichever one I think that
is. As a workflow, this sucks. We can do better. So let&rsquo;s put everything in
a file, and have lots of files. Don&rsquo;t worry, we&rsquo;ll optimise that away.</p>

<p>Does putting everything in a little script seem like too much architecture? If
it does, No Magento developer is <strong>ever</strong> allowed to tell me that a little bit
more architecture is a bad thing. On this note, can we stop with putting
JavaScript in attributes of buttons and things? It&rsquo;s a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Guide/HTML/Event_attributes">Bad Idea</a>.</p>

<h3>What Would be Better?</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve got three priorities in this game: Correctness, Niceness, Performance.</p>

<h4>Correctness</h4>

<p>I want some measure of guarantee that my script loads after another script
whose existence I&rsquo;m assuming.</p>

<p>Second, I want to export less global variables. Globals are bad news for a
number of reasons. If we pick sane ones, they may be overwritten by some other
sane global variable. Global variables are impossible to minify. With all the
other performance tools available to us, this is a minor one, but with mobile
and responsive design, we&rsquo;re once again back to a time when every bite matters.</p>

<h4>Niceness</h4>

<p>Magento has a way of doing things, and it generally prioritises developer time
above server costs. That&rsquo;s how things got this time, and it&rsquo;s a good priority to
have, because we build websites quickly. Serving up JavaScript is not going to
be where our servers spend the most time.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t want to debug minified code. I don&rsquo;t even want to debug concatenated
code. Magento does this well, and we shouldn&rsquo;t lose that. Performance has to be
an option. Debugging event listeners in minified jQuery is horrible, and I don&rsquo;t
ever want to have to deal with that problem.</p>

<h4>Performance</h4>

<p>I want scripts to be cached well, so that performance is good. I want them to be
delayed so that content loads before. I want, by and large, for scripts to
change as little of the styling as possible, so that their loading doesn&rsquo;t
effect too much of a change in the content. Since we&rsquo;ve always assumed that
scripts load first, it&rsquo;s going to be a bit of a change in our mindset. I think
we can do it. It&rsquo;s for the good of our websites.</p>

<h3>What Are the Options?</h3>

<p>There are a few things we can do, and this isn&rsquo;t all going to happen overnight.
Let&rsquo;s start by making every new piece of code we write better. We&rsquo;ll work on
the old stuff later, because there&rsquo;s a lot of it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about a good transport format for modules. My first
idea was to use <a href="https://github.com/amdjs/amdjs-api/wiki/AMD">AMD</a>, but after a brief discussion with <a href="https://twitter.com/getify">@getify</a>, I was
given cause to reconsider.</p>

<p>AMD is well established, and many libraries use it already, so that integration
is a lot easier. Tools exist to map dependency trees into script loading, too.</p>

<p>A custom transport would be lighter weight, and a lot easier to integrate with
old code. The dependency management would be file based rather than module
based, and modules could be implemented as a layer over that, in some IIFE. This
solves my immediate problem of demanding that <code>validation.js</code> is loaded before
my script.</p>

<p>As for what kind of custom transport format, I&rsquo;m thinking something like this:</p>

<p>```javascript</p>

<pre><code>//@require js/prototype/validation.js

!function validatePersonalisationOptions (deps) {
    // do stuff 
}()
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Of course, the IIFE at the bottom is completely optional. This would reduce
refactoring all of Magento&rsquo;s JavaScript to a few comments in the core files,
and for that change, we all get a lot more structure and reliability about how
our scripts load.</p>

<p>Whatever I choose, I&rsquo;d then want to implement some block interface for adding
scripts to the bottom of the body. I don&rsquo;t want to change core Magento templates
for this, and the closest we&rsquo;re given is <code>before_body_end</code>, which is okay,
although not ideal, because content can appear after that. That way, I can take
the time to implement some optimisations on the server side. Of course, all of
this optimisation is made really hard by using PHP. The web community has made
loads of really good tools for optimising JavaScript, and I&rsquo;d want to maintain
as much interoperability as possible, maybe by encouraging people to use Grunt,
or some other build tool. I&rsquo;ll have to think about that some more.</p>

<p>I mentioned that I&rsquo;d like less inline scripting, and for everything to go into a
file. While it&rsquo;s all good for me to say something like that, let&rsquo;s take a moment
to think about why it&rsquo;s so common: there exists no good way of getting data,
like product information, from the server to the client. We can&rsquo;t compile
JavaScript files.</p>

<p>I had two ideas. One, that I tried out recently, was to send the data I need
down to the client after the fact, using AJAX. This certainly works pretty well
for some cases. It&rsquo;s a really lightweight controller, and this method can go a
long way for data that we can load asynchronously.</p>

<p>But we might sometimes need to load data synchronously. My preferred interface
for this is the layout xml, where I can bind certain data to a script, and that
gets sent down and somehow assigned as a variable before the script is run.
Like all of the layout xml, the data in question could be the result of a call
to a helper method, which gives us the power to do anything. The implementation
of this has tripped me up a little bit, though.</p>

<p>Annoyingly, this would be a perfect use case for the <code>with</code> statement, but
that&rsquo;s been deprecated, so I&rsquo;m going to not use it. I&rsquo;m thinking that if I
transform scripts from the above form into something like</p>

<p>```javascript</p>

<pre><code>!function registerExternalVars () {
    var foo = { /* JSON */ };

    !function validatePersonalisationOptions (deps) {
        // do stuff
    }();
}();
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Notice that I&rsquo;m using the module transport specified above. This isn&rsquo;t strictly
necessary, but if you&rsquo;re planning on exporting any globals, you probably want
to be assigning them as properties of the global object, otherwise they won&rsquo;t be
globals anymore. I&rsquo;m okay with this, since I&rsquo;m really only looking for a
solution for new code. Old code can stay the way it is for the time being.</p>

<p>This works nicely, but it means we can&rsquo;t cache these things on the back end,
since the values might change sometimes. So it seems best to factor these data
out into some other object, which is accessible. I&rsquo;m still working out how best
to control access to that, though. I don&rsquo;t want it to be visible to anyone on
the outside.</p>

<p>So, there we have it. I finally wrote down what I thought about JavaScript in
Magento.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
